Hi everyone and welcome
to the Myocarditis,
Pericarditis and Cardiac
Tumors Lecture. My name is Alec
Tufeksis, one of your
academic medicine scholars.
This is an adaptation
from the lecture of
the same name given
by Dr. Petku in the
years prior so just
wanted to give him a shout
out for letting me
work on this lecture.
Much of this information in
this lecture was taken from
Robin's Pathology, I highly
recommend reading it for
any clarifications that
you need. It is only a few
pages, and of course, feel
free to email me with any
questions that you have.
I'll be happy to answer them.
Here are your
session objectives.
At the end of the
session, you'll be able
to discuss myocarditis,
how it manifests
clinically, its causes
and consequences.
You'll be able to grasp
pericardial diseases
and know what causes
them, as well as
describe their
morphology and histology,
and summarize the
various cardiac tumors.
You can use this slide
to guide your studies.
First off, it is
important to precisely
know the definition
of myocarditis.
The definition is
histopathologic in nature
and is described by
the Dallas criteria.
This criteria is the
presence of an inflammatory
infiltrate of the myocardium
with necrosis and or
degeneration of adjacent
myocytes, not typical of ischemic
damage associated with
coronary artery disease.
After a heart attack,
there are dead myocardial
cells. The healing
process and scar formation
involve an influx of
immune cells. Although
there is inflammation
and myocyte necrosis,
in this instance, it
is not myocarditis.
The clinical manifestations
of myocarditis
range greatly from
virtually asymptomatic and
self-limited to
fulminant, meaning sudden
escalation of symptoms
with severe heart failure.
About half of the
time, an etiologic
agent is never
identified. However,
when there is, it
is usually a virus.
Other significant
causes are bacteria,
fungi, parasites,
cardiotoxins, drugs,
and systemic
autoimmune disorders.
Here are histological
pictures of myocarditis.
Notice the inflammatory
infiltrate of
immune cells within
the myocardium.
With the left picture, the
white arrow is pointing
to a lymphocyte, and the
black arrow is pointing
to myocyte necrosis. The
picture on the right shows
a more zoomed-out
histopathology of myocarditis.
Just some quick
epidemiology of myocarditis.
It has a prevalence of
10.2 to 105.6 per 100
,000. The wide range for
this prevalence is due
to the uncertainty
surrounding true prevalence
and potential underdiagnosis
of the disease.
Myocarditis is most
dangerous within the
first year of life, as
the disease presentation
is more likely to be
fulminant in nature.
There is thought to be
a protective effect of
natural hormonal influences
on immune responses
in women when compared
to men when it comes
to myocarditis, which
is correlated to the
increased death rates
in males after age 15.
The diagnosis of
myocarditis can be very
difficult, especially in
areas that lack proper
diagnostic tools.
and without the gold
standard endomyocardial
biopsy, which is another
reason for the wide
range and prevalence.
Clinically, there
is a wide range of
symptoms that
accompany myocarditis.
A patient may be completely
asymptomatic and not even
know that they have
inflammation of the heart. On
the opposite side of the
spectrum, they may develop
dilated cardiomyopathy or
arrhythmias that can cause
sudden death, which
describes more of a fulminant
clinical course. The symptoms
that lie between these
two extremes include fatigue,
dyspnea, palpitations,
precordial
discomfort, and fever.
The trickiness of diagnosis
increases even more
when myocarditis symptoms
mimic acute MI symptoms.
Patients can present
with chest pain, EKG
abnormalities, and elevated
cardiac biomarkers.
diagnosis of myocarditis
requires clues from both the
history and physical and
diagnostic tests although
not regularly used an
endomyocardial biopsy or EMB is
the gold standard it is
done if other non-invasive
modalities cannot reach a
diagnosis and if the results
of the EMB significantly
impact patient management.
It is performed by inserting
a bioptome into the
venous system and into
the right ventricle, or a
sample is taken and can be
viewed for histopathology.
EKG, CRP, troponin,
chest radiograph, and
echocardiogram are
always needed when
myocarditis is suspected.
One of the methods for
determining if a patient
is presenting with acute
coronary syndrome or
myocarditis is to take the
ratio of CRP to troponin.
Those with acute coronary
syndrome will have much
lower CRP to troponin ratio,
meaning the CRP levels are
lower and troponins are higher
compared to myocarditis,
which has higher CRP
levels and lower troponins.
If acute coronary
syndrome cannot be ruled
out, then you may need
coronary angiography.
Additionally, a definitive
diagnosis cannot
be made without an
EMB that meets Dallas
criteria, as well as an
EMB sample that indicates
myocarditis with
immunohistochemical stains.
If myocarditis is
likely based on history
and physical and non
-invasive tests, then it's
termed clinically
suspected myocarditis.
Myocarditis can be
classified into four distinct
clinical presentations with
their own unique courses.
The two acute forms
are on this slide,
acute and fulminant.
Acute myocarditis is usually
caused by a viral infection.
We will go into exactly
what viruses tend
to cause myocarditis
later in this lecture.
It occurs two to four
weeks after exposure.
This clinical manifestation
has the highest
risk of dilated
cardiomyopathy in the
future among acute
versions of myocarditis.
Physical exam of acute
myocarditis may show
a third heart sound,
such as S3 or S4, which
are indicative of
pathology of the heart.
Mitral or tricuspid
insufficiency murmurs can be
heard from dilation of the
heart and separation of
the valve leaflets if dilated
cardiomyopathy occurs.
A pericardial friction
rub may be heard if
there is also
superimposed pericarditis.
Heart failure findings, such
as fluid overload, may result.
Fulminant myocarditis has
a much more severe acute
presentation and much
quicker onset of symptoms.
It usually results
within two weeks
of exposure to the
etiologic agent.
It is accompanied by
severe dysfunction of
the left ventricle,
leading to heart failure.
Histology will show
many areas of active
inflammation and necrosis
of cardiomyocytes.
Patients either die from
the severity of the heart
dysfunction or surprisingly
fully recover, having a
better long-term prognosis
than acute myocarditis.
These are the two
versions of chronic
myocarditis that you
are responsible for.
Chronic active myocarditis has
symptoms present
after two weeks.
There is a long-term
active inflammatory
infiltrate within the
myocardium that ends up
activating fibroblasts,
leading to fibrosis.
As a result of this,
the heart is at risk of
developing restrictive
cardiomyopathy, as
opposed to the dilated
cardiomyopathy that
you see with acute and
fulminant myocarditis.
The top right picture
shows the inflammatory
infiltrate and fibrosis
within the myocardium.
This takes time,
however, developing in
two to four years
after presentation.
Chronic persistent, as
the name suggests, is
persistent infiltrate
of immune cells and
persistent symptoms of
myocarditis. However,
there is no ventricular
dysfunction present.
Now that we have
discussed how a person
with myocarditis
presents, we will go
into what agents
leads the condition.
These are viral,
bacterial, fungal,
parasitic, and immune
-mediated causes.
The most common
cause of myocarditis,
specifically acute
myocarditis, when an
etiology is identified,
are viruses.
The viruses most
associated with myocarditis
are enteroviruses,
specifically Coxsackie B.
This virus is also
associated with pleurodynia,
or severe spastic pain
caused by myositis of
the abdomen or chest,
as well as GI distress,
fever,
headache, sore throat,
and aseptic meningitis.
Recently, myocarditis
caused by parvovirus
B19 and HHV-6 have
become more common.
CMV, HIV, and influenza
can also cause
myocarditis, although
less commonly.
Identification of the
virus uses serologic
studies, which are
much less invasive
than the rarely used
viral nucleic acid
sequencing obtained from
myocardial biopsies.
Viruses damage the
heart via two methods,
direct damage to the
cardiomyocytes by
the virus or secondary
damage caused by the
immune cells that
respond to the virus.
The picture on the right
shows the Coxsackie
B virus obtained from
an electron microscope.
Bacteria may also
cause myocarditis.
Chlamydia, Rickettsia,
and Neisseria are all
potential etiologic
agents. However, the most
important ones to know for
board exams are Borrelia
burgdorferi, which
causes Lyme disease, and
Crinobacterium diphtheria,
which causes diphtheria.
Borrelia burgdorferi
is a spirochete
spread by the exotis tick.
The bacteria infiltrate
the heart and can cause an
inflammatory response termed
Lyme carditis. The most
classic presentation of this
is a rapidly changing AV
block, meaning the EKG may
first show first degree,
then second degree, and
progress to complete heart
block, then return back to
first degree within minutes.
Diphtheria is commonly
associated with pseudomembrane
and can form on the tonsils
and throat by destroying
healthy tissue as well as
causing a swollen neck.
Diphtheria produces a
toxin that can leak into
the lymphatic and
hematologic systems and can
cause damage to the heart,
leading to myocarditis.
Diphtheria toxin
damages tissues by
inhibiting elongation
factor 2, or EF2,
which is important
for protein synthesis.
Next is fungi.
This etiology is very
rare, but most commonly
seen in immunocompromised
individuals. So the
risk of fungal myocarditis
is highest in those
with long-term, broad
-spectrum antibiotic usage,
corticosteroid usage, invasive
procedures, and those
with HIV infection.
Definitive diagnosis is
very difficult based on
non-invasive diagnostic
tests since the clinical
signs are absent and blood
tests are often negative.
The most common
fungal causes are
invasive Candida or
Aspergillus species.
On EMB, you may see the
hyphae, as in the case of
aspergillus, or pseudohyphae,
as in the case of candida.
The picture in the
slide shows invasive
aspergillus, which has
spread to the heart, causing
myocarditis. You can
see the septate hyphae.
Here are the most common
parasitic causes of
myocarditis. The most heavily
tested cause of parasitic
myocarditis is Chagas
disease. This is the most
common in Latin America
due to the presence of
the reduvid bug, also known
as the kissing bug, that
spreads the parasite
called trypanosoma cruzi.
They get their
name because they
tend to bite people's faces.
Their urine and feces
carries the parasite,
which can enter the bite
site, causing infection.
Chagas disease usually
comes in phases, with
the acute phase
accompanied usually with
minor symptoms, but can
occasionally be severe
and show signs of CNS
involvement and death.
A characteristic nodule
called the chagoma at
the site of infection
may occur, and if it is
on the eyelid, this is
known as Romagna's sign.
After the acute
phase, which lasts 8
to 12 weeks, the
indeterminate phase
occurs where there
are no symptoms.
The chronic phase
occurs 10 to 20 years
after initial infection.
From the years of
parasite proliferation
in the tissues, patients
develop the characteristic
cardiomegaly,
megaesophagus, and megacolon.
On biopsy, you can see
pseudocyst dilations
within the fibers in
the amastigote form.
The parasite becomes
flagellated when they burst out
of infected cells, which
can be seen on the left.
Toxoplasma gondii
and trichinella
may also lead to myocarditis.
Myocarditis may also
be immune-mediated.
Myocarditis can occur
following a viral infection
with viruses discussed
before, such as Coxsackie
B and other enteroviruses,
parvovirus B19, HHV6.
In this version, the
inflammatory infiltrate is
largely lymphocytic in
nature, which ends up damaging
the heart tissue. If the
inflammatory infiltrate on
EMB has a high proportion
of eosinophils, you would
suspect that the myocarditis
was triggered by a
hypersensitivity response,
most likely from medications.
Ampicillin and
thiazide diuretics are
notable examples of
potential causes.
A very serious immune-mediated
myocarditis that usually
takes on a fulminant
course is giant
cell myocarditis.
There is no known direct
cause of this type, so
it is idiopathic, but
there is an increased risk
among those with concurrent
autoimmune diseases.
EMB will show multinucleated
giant cells as seen in
the picture with a mix of
lymphocytes, eosinophils,
plasma cells, and macrophages.
To give an idea of
severity of this disease,
according to one study, the
rate of death or cardiac
transplant was 89%, and the
median survival from onset
of symptoms was 5.5 months.
Continuing our discussion
on immune causes,
the immune system of
the host can attack a
donor heart, causing
transplant rejection.
An EMB will show
inflammatory infiltrate and
cardiomyocyte cell death, so
this would be myocarditis.
Additionally, rheumatic fever
caused after a streptococcal
infection, specifically
group A strep, may lead
to myocarditis. This occurs
due to a highly antigenic
protein released by the
bacteria called M protein,
an NABG, also known as N
-acetyl-beta-D-glucosamine.
Antibodies against
protein M can cross-react
with the myosin within
the cardiomyocytes,
leading to damage in
antibodies against NABG
likely to play a role
in valvular injury.
The histopathology of
heart tissue and rheumatic
fever will show Ashkoff
bodies, which are granulomas,
as well as Anishkoff cells,
also known as caterpillar
cells, which are macrophages
with ovoid nucleus.
The elongated nucleus somewhat
resembles a caterpillar.
An Ashkoff body and
Anishkoff cell can
be seen in the
picture on the right.
Myocarditis may also be seen
in inflammatory systemic
disorders. In all cases,
inflammatory cells
may infiltrate the myocardium,
causing myocarditis.
The final cause
of myocarditis we
will discuss is
direct cardiotoxins.
They induce myocarditis through
mechanisms that are
not well elucidated.
You'll see this with
antineoplastic agents and
treatments like anthracyclines
and cyclophosphamide,
as well as radiation. In
addition, illicit drugs
like cocaine, heavy alcohol
use, certain metals like
copper, lead, and iron
can lead to myocarditis.
To give some visuals, on the
top right is cocaine, and
below is arsenic, and below
that is doxorubicin, and
anthracycline, which has a
characteristic red color.
The next section of this
lecture is pericardial
disease. This has to do
with the pericardium,
which is the sac
surrounding the heart that
provides mechanical
protection and lubrication
between the heart and the
surrounding structures.
Between the heart and
the pericardium is the
pericardial space,
or a small amount of
serous fluid, which
allows that lubrication.
The disease of the pericardium
and the pericardial
space occur from either
direct disease or
indirectly through systemic
diseases. It manifests
from fluid buildup in
the pericardial space,
which is also known as
pericardial effusion,
inflammation of the pericardium,
termed pericarditis,
and or fibrous constriction,
which occurs when
excess fibrin deposition
happens, and the
pericardium becomes
thickened and non-compliant.
normally the pericardial
space contains around 50
milliliters of serous fluid
if you were to see the fluid
it would appear like the
fluid in the picture at
the top right this yellowish
color is termed straw
colored when fluids such as
serious fluid or other foods
like blood pus or lymphatic
fluid build up in the
pericardial space it is
called pericardial effusion
the pericardium has the
ability to adapt to changes
in the volume of pericardial
fluid but only if
it is a slow buildup it
remodels and gets bigger
allowing for cardiac function
to go unaffected some
patients may not even
know that they have a
pericardial effusion if they
have less than 500 milliliters
and it is chronic x-ray
will show an enlarged
heart shadow and is
known as a water bottle
configuration, as you can
see in the top right picture.
Pericardial effusions
are very dangerous as
the fluid in the pericardial
space accumulates
very rapidly to the
point where the fluid
compresses the heart so
much that it cannot fill
properly. This is termed
cardiac tamponade.
A commonly tested version
of this is hemopericardium
or accumulation of blood in
the space from the rupture
of the heart after an MI or
a type A aortic dissection
if it includes the
pericardium only 200 to 300
milliliters is required for
this presentation since the
pericardium does not have any
time to adapt to the increased
fluid these are the forms
of acute pericarditis
you are responsible for
knowing they are caused by
different etiologies and
present differently both
macroscopically and on histology
the terms before the word
pericarditis describe what
you will see grossly if you
were to look at the pericardium
and pericardial space.
There are also chronic forms of
pericarditis, which
we will go into later.
First off is serous
pericarditis. This one
tends to occur due
to mainly systemic
inflammatory diseases
and not from infection.
There's a collection
of excess serous fluid
in the pericardial
space, which can be seen
in the picture on the
top right of a heart
from a patient with
rheumatoid arthritis.
Besides rheumatoid
arthritis, you can
see serous pericarditis
and rheumatic
fever, systemic
lupus erythematosus,
scleroderma, tumors,
and uremia, among others.
There may be an infectious
process going on, but not
directly in the pericardial
space or pericardium.
By extension, there is
irritation, which can cause
mild inflammatory infiltrate
and an increase in serious
fluid accumulation. If
infection is involved, be
careful about evolving into
either serofibrinous or
suppurative pericarditis,
which we will soon discuss.
Viruses can also cause serous
pericarditis, and commonly
someone will have a viral
infection of the upper
airway or the lungs. It is
most likely not a direct
infection of the pericardium,
and direct infections
are rare and are usually
associated with myocarditis.
Tumors lead to serous
pericarditis through
invasion of the
lymphatics. There is a mild
inflammatory infiltrate
involved consisting of
lymphocytes, and pericardial
fluid analysis may
contain neoplastic cells
when cancer is involved.
Next up is serofibrinous
and fibrinous pericarditis.
Serofibrinous involves
both serous effusion
with fibrin deposition,
while fibrinous is mainly
fibrin deposition
covering the pericardium.
How it appears is classically
termed bread-and-butter
pericarditis, since it kind
of looks as if two pieces
of buttered bread were
pressed together then pulled
apart. This is the most common
type of pericarditis and is
associated with acute
myocardial infarction, uremia,
rheumatic fever,
lupus, trauma, and
after cardiac surgery.
Dressler syndrome is a topic
commonly found in questions
and happens usually one to
six weeks after myocardial
infarction or after heart
surgery. It is thought
to happen from release of
antigens from the pericardium
and heart that our immune
system detects as foreign.
The classic sign of
pericarditis is the friction
rub herb with a stethoscope.
The patient may also
assume the tripod position
where they lean forward
supporting their upper
body on the knees or other
surface. This is seen
mostly in respiratory
distress, but in a patient
with chest pain without labor
breathing, this can be
a sign of pericarditis.
When pus is seen
surrounding the heart, this
indicates that an active
infection is present.
This can be direct
infection from trauma or
surgery, or it can
spread from a neighboring
structure, like from a
pneumonia of the lungs,
mediastinal infection,
or abscess of the heart.
Bacteria can also travel
through the blood to the
pericardium, or through the
lymphatics. the picture on
the right demonstrates
purulent fluid and the
pericardial sac with erythematous
changes of the pericardium
here we have hemorrhagic
pericarditis if you were
to open up the pericardium
and look inside you'll
see blood with fibrinous
or suppurative effusion you
will see this with mostly
malignancy and you'll see
neoplastic cells on pericardial
tap bacterial infection
can also cause this most
commonly, tuberculosis.
There's also a chance
at developing this form
if the patient has an
increased tendency to
bleed. This is known
as bleeding diastasis.
Anytime there is surgery
and there is a risk of
damaging the vasculature
in the area, bleeding
and inflammation can
result, and if it is in this
area of the pericardium,
this form can manifest.
The picture on the
right shows the
blood and the
fibrinous adhesions
connecting the heart
to the pericardium.
Here are the two chronic or
healed forms of pericarditis
that we will discuss.
They are adhesive
mediastino-pericarditis and
constrictive pericarditis.
Chronic pericarditis is
associated with fibrosis
of the pericardium, the
level of which varies
from a few unobstructive
fibrous thickenings
called soldier's plaques
to large mesh-like
adhesions that take up the
whole pericardial space.
Since this is chronic,
the heart is still
able to function and
keep the patient alive
despite what is going
on with the pericardium.
This is because the pericardium
has time to remodel.
Adhesive mediastinal
pericarditis is interesting
because it involves adhesions
on the external surface
of the parietal or outside
layer of the pericardium
as opposed to the serosal
layer or inside layer.
These adhesions form
as a result of previous
infectious pericarditis,
previous surgery, or
radiation. It can attach
to structures surrounding
the heart so that
with each beat these
adhesions become taut and
strain cardiac function.
The heart will, as a
result, have systolic
dysfunction, and in some
cases there will be retraction
of the rib cage and
diaphragm during systole
from the heart pulling
on these structures.
Pulsus paradoxus
may happen since
the heart is adherent
to the lungs.
With this strain on
the heart, it forces
it to work harder to
pump. As a result, the
heart hypertrophies
and dilation occurs.
To end our discussion on
pericarditis, the last
chronic form is
constrictive pericarditis. A
thick fibrocalcific scar
encases the heart, limiting
its ability to fill
properly during diastole.
This also results in a
decrease in cardiac output
since the preload and
stroke volume are decreased.
This mimics restrictive
cardiomyopathy.
The scar can get so
big that it can be 1
cm in thickness, which
is termed concretiocordus
since it resembles
a plaster mold.
Neither hypertrophy or
dilation of the heart can occur
since the scar is so
noncompliant and dense so that
the heart cannot adapt to
the demands of the body.
The main causes of
constrictive pericarditis
are idiopathic in
nature, heart surgery,
radiation of the chest,
or tuberculosis.
Shifting gears, we will
now discuss our final
topic, which is cardiac
tumors. Luckily,
the primary cardiac
tumors are rare and mostly
benign. It is far more likely
that tumors found in the
heart are metastases from
elsewhere in the body.
Although rare,
myxomas are the most
common primary cardiac
tumor, followed by
fibromas, lipomas,
papillary fibroelastomas,
and rhabdomyomas.
Sarcomas are the malignant
primary cardiac tumors,
of which angiosarcomas
are the most common.
Symptoms of the
benign primary cardiac
tumors are typically
characteristic of where
they are located in
the heart and can arise
from obstruction,
thromboembolic events,
conduction defects,
and blockage
of the coronary arteries.
It is also important
to note, if a
tumor is located in
the left, you may
see symptoms of
left heart failure,
and if they are on
the right side, you
may see symptoms of
right heart failure.
Starting off with
myxomas, again, they
are the most common
primary cardiac tumor.
These tumors are associated
with germline mutations
of an alpha regulatory
subunit on cyclic AMP
-dependent protein kinase
type 1, also called PRKAR1A.
This enzyme is a
tumor suppressor gene.
Individuals with this
mutation develop what is known
as CARNI complex, which
is an autosomal dominant
condition comprising of
myxomas of the heart and skin,
hyperpigmentation of the skin,
and endocrine overactivity.
These tumors are thought
to arise from multipotent
mesenchymal stem cells
since the cells have
characteristics of
primitive cardiac myocytes
and endothelial cell
precursors. It is important
to know where the
different benign primary
cardiac tumors are typically
found. In this case,
myxomas are usually
found in the left atrium.
An example of this is
seen in the picture.
Just based on the size,
you would imagine that that
myxoma may have led to
symptoms of obstruction.
Histology of this tumor
shows stellated, fusiform,
and polygonal cells in an
amorphous myxoid matrix.
Here is another picture of
a myxoma located in the left
atrium of the heart and
the slated fusiform cells
and polygonal cells in the
myxoid matrix on the right.
The second most
common primary benign
cardiac tumor is
the cardiac fibroma.
As the name suggests,
it is composed
of connective tissue
and fibroblasts.
This cardiac tumor is
mostly found in the
left ventricle, and
just like myxomas,
the symptoms arise
from the same things.
Obstruction, coronary
artery compromise,
thromboembolic events,
and conduction defects.
This one is also
associated with a syndrome
called nevoid basal
cell carcinoma
syndrome, also known
as Gorlin syndrome.
People develop basal
cell carcinomas,
odontogenic keratocysts,
which are located
in the jaw, and 2 to
20% of individuals
with this condition
get cardiac fibromas.
This all occurs from a mutation
in PTCH1 tumor suppressor gene.
This picture on the
right highlights the
location of the left
ventricle as well as the
histology of connective
tissue and fibroblasts.
Lipomas are usually seen
in the skin, but they
can occur elsewhere in
the body, even the heart.
Just like those that occur
in the skin, they are
composed of mature adipocytes
and tend to form in
the left ventricle or
right atrium of the heart.
People with cardiac lipomas
might not even know that
they have one, but just like
the previously mentioned
primary tumors, if they get
big enough, they can obstruct
blood flow within the
heart, leading to symptoms.
There have even been
cases of cardiac
lipomas that compressed
the superior vena
cava when they involved
the right atrium.
The picture on the lower
right shows a fairly
big cardiac lipoma
that was removed, most
likely from severe
symptoms of obstruction.
The primary benign
cardiac tumor that you
will find on valves
are fibroelastomas.
The exact pathogenesis of these
tumors is not quite understood.
However, it is believed that
they are hamartomas, which
are abnormal growths made
up of the same tissue
from which it grows, which
is why it is composed of
collagen and surrounded by a
layer of endothelial cells,
just like the cardiac valves.
However, there is another
theory that these lesions
are acquired and begin
as microthrombi that join
its sites of minor
endothelial damage on valvular
surfaces that evolve into
these types of tumors.
embolization is often
a primary concern with
this cardiac tumor
and can lead to stroke
or myocardial infarction
if they occlude
coronary artery orifices
and may lead to death.
Due to the risk of stroke
and MI, from the left side
of papillary fibroelastomas,
they tend to be removed
with surgery. The decision
to remove the right side of
ones is a more difficult
decision that pros and cons.
Fibroelastomas are classically
described as having an
appearance of a sea anemone
as you can see in the
picture the left. They have
a central stalk and a frond
like arms projecting outwards.
On histology you'll see
primarily collagen with an
outer layer of endothelium.
The last major benign
primary cardiac tumor we will
talk about is the rhabdomyoma.
This one is the most
common primary cardiac
tumor in childhood. It is
important to know that this
tumor is associated with
tuberous sclerosis from
mutations in TSC1 and TSC2.
Other findings in
individuals with tuberous
sclerosis are ash leaf
spots, chagrin patches,
cortical tumors in
the brain, giant cell
astrocytomas, and
renal angiomyolipomas.
Cardiac rhabdomyomas
are commonly not found
as a solitary mass and
are typically found to
involve ventricles and
sometimes the atria.
The characteristic
finding on histology is
the spider cell, which
has a small central
nuclei and abundant glycogen
-rich clear cytoplasm
with fibrillar
processes containing
sarcomeres that radiate
to the edge of the cell.
With their location
within the heart muscle,
they can present with
arrhythmias and heart
failure, although most
are as asymptomatic.
It is important to
note that these tumors
can spontaneously
regress over time.
On the left is the spider
cell with the fibrillar
processes that radiate to the
margins, and on the right,
you'll see multiple rhabdomyomas
in the heart muscle.
here are some very rare
benign primary cardiac tumors
that are interesting the
first is the cystic tumor the
AV node which as the name
suggests is found in the AV
nodal region with its
involvement in the cardiac
conduction system this tumor
can result in sudden death
there are also hemangiomas
which are highly vascular
tumors neurofibromas have
plexiform and scattered spindle
cells and teratomas which
have all germinal layers
present and are found in
the young a very interesting
tumor of the heart is the
lyomyoma which can be primary
but there are some that
hypothesize that cardiac
lyomyomas are actually
metastases from lyomyomas of the
uterus that travel through
the inferior vena cava lastly
are also lymphangiomas that
have that contain vascular
malformations with lymphatic
elements just to emphasize
these tumors are extremely
rare here we have malignant
primary cardiac tumors
since these cancers are
derived from supportive and
connective tissues they are
classified as sarcomas the
sarcoma is named depending
on what tissue type is growing
malignantly angiosarcomas
are the most common malignant
primary cardiac tumor
and are usually found on
the right side of the heart.
Angio implies
that the cancer is
formed from blood
or lymph vessels.
To emphasize how
rare that these are,
there were only around
100,000 primary cardiac
tumors reported in the
span of 12 years, of which
only 0.8% were malignant,
according to one study.
Finally, we have
metastatic tumors.
These are much more
likely to be found in
the heart than primary
cardiac tumors.
Lung, breast, and GI
carcinomas may spread to
the heart as well as
lymphomas and leukemias.
The cancer that is most
likely to spread to the
heart is malignant
melanoma as you can see in
the picture of the heart
on the lower right.
Notice the extent and number of
the metastases
within that heart.
When metastases invade
the heart tissue it
leads to fibrosis
and stiffening of the
muscle leading to
restrictive cardiomyopathy.
As with any cancer that
grows within the myocardium,
it can interfere with
the conduction system,
leading to heart blocks
or bundle branch blocks.
Here is the summary slide.
I just want to emphasize
that myocarditis is
caused by many different
infectious and non-infectious
causes, and that it
may lead to dilated
cardiomyopathy or restrictive
if it is the chronic active
form. It is important
to note that the EMB is
the gold standard for
diagnosis. However, it is
very rarely used if getting
one does not alter how
the patient is treated.
Pericardial disease
involves the pericardium and
the pericardial space.
There is inflammation with
or without pericardial
effusion. It may be acute or
chronic and most involve
some level of fibrosis.
Lastly, it is important
to know primary cardiac
tumors are rare with the
majority being benign.
They could be asymptomatic
but may lead to obstruction
or conduction issues.
Please familiarize
yourself with the most
common locations for each.
Thank you so much for
your attention. Here
is the lecture feedback
form. Please don't
hesitate to email me
with any questions that
you have on the subject.
Good luck to you
all in your studies and
your future careers.